Guide to the McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center Vertical File, 1948-1991
The John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center Vertical File 1948-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center
121.5 Linear Feet About 72,900 Items
The McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center was established in 1948 as a sales service for customers of the McGraw-Hill Publications Company.
This large vertical file, developed by the McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center, spans the years 1948 through 1991 and contains published articles, books, research studies, speech transcripts, and other materials on the subjects of marketing, sales, advertising, and corporate operations.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center Vertical File were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1999.
Historical Note
The McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center was established in 1948 as a sales service for customers of the McGraw-Hill Publications Company. It was maintained through 1991.
A guide to the vertical file was developed by Ranulph F. Norman, Director of the Marketing Information Center, and published in 1985 under the title Advertising/Marketing Library Index. The present finding aid represents an electronic version of that paper guide.
Collection Overview
This large vertical file, compiled and indexed by the McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center (MIC), spans the years 1948 through 1991 and contains published articles, books, research studies, speech transcripts, and other materials on the subjects of marketing, sales, advertising, and corporate governance. Material was gathered from about 125 sources, chiefly regularly-published administration, advertising, and marketing periodicals.
The collection is divided into five series: Administration; Advertising; International Operations; Marketing; and Sales. Additionally, the Alphabetical, Topical, Keyword Index is available to aid browsing.
Structure of the Finding Aid
All descriptions and references in this inventory were written by the MIC and have been retained. The original organization of the vertical file and numbering system of the index have also been retained. Major topics are arranged in increments of five. For example: ADV 0 (Advertising's Role, Function, and Influence); ADV 5 (Advertising Agencies); ADV 10 (Advertising Appropriations); ADV 15 (Attitudes Towards Advertising), and so on through ADV 55 (Advertising Volume). These increments of five are standard throughout all the major areas except Administration (ADM).
Primary subdivisions are created by placing a colon following the 0, 5, 10, 15, etc., and adding a number starting with 1 and up the line as high as required (e.g., ADV 5:1). Secondary subdivisions are created by placing a hyphen after the number following the colon and again adding numbers as high as needed (e.g., ADV 5:1-1). Further subdivisions are developed by inserting a decimal point and number (e.g., ADV 5:1-1.1). Additional decimal points and numbers are added to subdivide as far as necessary (e.g., ADV 5:1-1.1.1).
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Marketing Information Center (McGraw-Hill Publications Company)
Advertising -- History
Advertising -- Research
Corporate governance
Management -- History
Management -- Research
Marketing -- History
Marketing research
Selling -- History
Speeches.
Vertical files.
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Administration Series (ADM), 22 Boxes
  Contains information on topics common to all areas of management.
  Headings are loosely arranged, first by organizational practices and then by major function--starting at the top with boards of directors, presidents and CEOs, and continuing on down the line alphabetically: economics management, executive management, financial management, general management, personnel management, planning management, public relations management, risk management, and so on. The strictly advertising/marketing/sales management activities are cataloged within the sections devoted specifically to those marketing areas.
  - ADM 0. Corporate Organization and Administration
    - ADM 0:1 Organization Standards and Practices, N.E.C. (criteria for organizational effectiveness) (Box 1)
      - 0:1-1 Organizational Charting
      - 0:1-2 Organizational Development (OD)
      - 0:1-3 Family Business Opportunities & Pitfalls (see also: ADM 0:2-4.16, Small Business, all subsections)
      - 0:1-4 Informal Organization
      - 0:1-5 Staff-Line/Staff-Staff Relationships
        Includes information on span of control.
      - 0:1-6 Decentralization/Divisionalization (see also: MKT 65:1, Industrial Purchasing Practices and Procedures for information on decentralized buying)
    - ADM 0:2 Managerial/Functional Structure; Departments and Tasks
      - 0:2-1 Boards of Directors: Challenges, Compensation
        (Only when in combination with other BOD topics), Composition, Dimensions, Practices, Responsibilities, N.E.C.
        - 0:2-1.1 Board Chairpersons
        - 0:2-1.2 Compensation of Directors (see also: ADM 0:2-1, Boards of Directors: Challenges, etc., for additional information; ADM 0:2-8.4, Compensation: Executive/Management and subsections) (Box 2)
        - 0:2-1.3 Ethnics and Women Board Members (see also: ADM 0:2-7.8, Ethnics/Minorities in Management; ADM 0:2-7.28, Women in Management)
        - 0:2-1.4 Legal Implications for Directors
        - 0:2-1.5 Outside Directors
        - 0:2-1.6 Presidents Vis-a-vis Boards of Directors
        - 0:2-1.7 Selecting Corporate Directors
        - 0:2-1.8 Worker Participation on BODs (see also: ADM 0:2-7.18, Participative Management)
      - 0:2-2 Presidents and CEOs
      - 0:2-3 Corporate Secretaries
      - [Advertising Management--see: MKT 40:1-2.1, Advertising Management, selected subsections; MKT 40:2-2, Advertising Departments]
      - [Communications (External) Management--see: ADM 0:2-10, Public Affairs/Relations, selected subsections; see also: MKT 40, MARKETING/COMMUNICATIONS ADMINISTRATION, selected subsections.]
      - [Communications (Internal) Management--see: ADM 0:2-10, Public Affairs/Relations, selected subsections; ADM 0:27.2, Communications Manager/Manager and Manager/Subordinate, Personal, Techniques - all subsections.]
      - [Customer Service Management--see: MKT 5:2-3, Customer Service Concept]
      - [Distribution Management--see: MKT 20.8, Traffic, Transportation and Distribution, Departments and Management, N.E.C. See also: MKT 20:7, Physical Distribution Management (Marketing Logistics)]
      - 0:2-4 Economics Management, N.E.C.
        - The American Competitive Enterprise System, N.E.C.
          Includes information on: economic theory; consumer attitudes towards business in general; the money supply; taxation; writings of a broad nature pertaining to the capitalistic system. See also: MKT 35:3, Consumerism.
          - 0:2-4.1.1 Black Capitalism
        - 0:2-4.2 Business/Corporate/Growth and Failure; Contributory Factors, N.E.C.
          See also: ADM 0:2-4.2.3, Mergers and Acquisitions as a Growth Factor; Mergers and Acquisitions, Planning Actions and Effects, N.E.C.; ADM 0:24.14, Rankings of U.S. Corporations, selected subsections
          - 0:2-4.2.1 Growth Records of U.S. Industries
          - 0:2-4.2.2 Failure/Survival Patterns and Rates, N.E.C.
            - 0:2-4.2.2.1 Failure/Survival Patterns and Rates, Dun & Bradstreet Analyses
          - 0:2-4.2.3 Mergers and Acquisitions as a Growth Factor: Mergers and Acquisitions; Planning, Actions, Effects, N.E.C. (Box 3)
            See also: ADM 0:2-4.10, Mergers, FTC and TCB Announcements and Statistical Reports; IOP 5:1-2, Joint Ventures Overseas; ADM 0:2-4.4, Concentration in Industry: Issues, Concepts, Convictions, Facts, selected subsections
            - 0:2-4.2.3.1 Effect of Mergers on Advertising
            - 0:2-4.2.3.2 Divestment/Divestiture
            - 0:2-4.2.3.3 Strategies and Tactics for Fighting a Takeover (making a company unattractive to a raider)
        - 0:2-4.3 Business History, N.E.C.
          Includes information on the how-to of writing company histories and the role of the corporate archivist.
          - 0:2-4.3.1 A History of American Business ( Fortune series, 1961-1962)
          - 0:2-4.3.2 The Business History ( Atlanta Economic Review, 1960-1961)
        - 0:2-4.4 Concentration in Industry: Concepts, Convictions, Issues, Facts, N.E.C.
          See also: ADM 0:2-4.11, Migration of Industry: The Geography of Manufacturing, selected subsections; ADM 0:2-4.2.3, Mergers and Acquisitions as a Growth Factor, N.E.C., for additional information on superconcentration
          - 0:2-4.4.1 The Advertising/Concentration Debate
          - 0:2-4.4.2 Concentration: Senate Subcommittee Hearings
          - 0:2-4.4.3 Concentration: Outside the U.S.
        - 0:2-4.5 Economic and Business Forecasting, N.E.C. (Box 4)
          Includes commentary on, and methods and techniques of, general business forecasting, e.g. econometric models. See also: MKT 50:2, Techniques of Marketing Research, all subsections; MKT 50:2-4, Market Analysis and Sales Forecasting, N.E.C. and selected subsections; ADM 0:2-9, Planning, Corporate, and subsections, for information on the long-range planning process
          - 0:2-4.5.1 Dictionaries of Economic Terms
        - 0:2-4.6 Business Cycles: Analyses, Causes, Suggested Cures
        - 0:2-4.7 Economic Forecasts
          See also: ADM 0:24.7.3, Economic Indicators, Selected; what they are and how they work
          - 0:2-4.7.1 Long-range Forecasts, N.E.C.
            - 0:2-4.7.1.1 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics series: The American Economy: Prospects for Growth to... (discontinued)
          - 0:2-4.7.2 Short-range Forecasts, N.E.C.
            - 0:2-4.7.2.1 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics series: The Business Outlook
          - 0:2-4.7.3 Economic Indicators: Selected
        - 0:2-4.8 Capital Expenditure Forecasts
          - 0:2-4.8.1 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: Annual Surveys; Business' Plans for New Plants and Equipment
            - 0:2-4.8.1.1 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: Special Checkups on Capital Spending Plans
            - 0:2-4.8.1.2 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: How Modern is American Industry (discontinued)
    - McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: Annual Survey of Overseas Operations of U.S. Industrial Companies
      See IOP 0:2-2
          - 0:2-4.8.2 Capital Expenditure Forecasts compiled by sources other than the McGraw-Hill Department of Economics; and/or commentary on capital expenditures/evaluations, etc.
        - 0:2-4.9 Inflation/Deflation: Causes, Consequences, Suggested Ways to Combat
        - 0:2-4.10 Mergers and Acquisitions: FTC and TCB (The Conference Board) Announcements and Statistical Reports
          See also: ADM 0:2-4.2.3, Mergers and Acquisitions as a Growth Factor; Mergers and Acquisitions; Planning, Actions, Effects, N.E.C. and subsections
        - 0:2-4.11 Migration of Industry: The Geography of Manufacturing, N.E.C.
          See also: ADM 0:2-10.7.2, Plant Location
          - 0:2-4.11.1 The Conference Board studies on Changing Location of Manufacturing Employment
          - 0:2-4.11.2 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: The Migration of Industry series (discontinued)
        - 0:2-4.12 Productivity, N.E.C. (Box 5)
          Includes information on quality circles; zero defects; see also: MKT 30, PRODUCTIVITY IN MARKETING)
          - 0:2-4.12.1 The Shorter Work Week (the 4-day week)
            - 0:2-4.12.1.1 Flexible Hours, Flextime (alternative work schedules)
          - 0:2-4.12.2 Governmental (Federal, State, Municipal) Productivity
        - 0:2-4.13 Profits: Their Place in the Economy, N.E.C.
          - 0:2-4.13.1 Business Week's surveys of corporate performance - the Corporate Scoreboard
          - 0:2-4.13.2 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: Annual Survey of Corporate Profit Trends (discontinued)
          - 0:2-4.13.3 Dun & Bradstreet, Inc.: Cost of Doing Business ... (Key Business Ratios; annual)
        - 0:2-4.14 Rankings of U.S. Corporations
          - 0:2-4.14.1 Black Enterprise: The Top 100 Black Businesses (annual)
          - 0:2-4.14.2 Financial World: America's Top Growth Companies (annual)
          - 0:2-4.14.3 Forbes: Annual Report on American Industry
            - 0:2-4.14.3.1 Forbes: The Forbes 500s The Dimensions of American Business)
          - 0:2-4.14.4 Fortune: The Fortune Directory of the 500 Largest U.S. Corporations (annual) (Box 6)
            - 0:2-4.14.4.1 The Fortune Directory of the Second 500 Largest Industrial Corporations has been suspended as of June, 1983. Decision as to make the suspension permanent has not been reached.
            - 0:2-4.14.4.2 Fortune: the Fortune Directory of the 50 Top Non-Industrial Companies; annual (series discontinued in 1983; see next entry)
            - 0:2-4.14.4.3 The Fortune Service 500
              Expanded ranking of the 50 Top Non-Industrial Corporations. Comprises three 100-company rankings of the largest diversified financial, diversified service, and commercial banking companies, and four 50-company rankings of the largest life insurance, retailing, transportation, and utility companies.
          - [The Fortune Directory of the Largest Industrials Outside the U.S.--see: IOP 0:7-3, Fortune; Largest Industrials Outside the U.S.]
          - 0:2-4.14.5 Inc. 100
            Annual ranking of the fastest-growing publicly held smaller corporations in the U.S.
          - 0:2-4.14.6 Ward's Directory of Largest U.S. Corporations
            - 0:2-4.14.6.1 Ward's Directory of Leading Private Companies
          - 0:2-4.14.7 Other Rankings, N.E.C.
            For example, The EISC, Economic Information Systems, Inc., Directories of Top U.S. Companies including private companies - Dun's Review [now, Dun's Business Month] The Dividend Achievers, Fortune's Directory of the 50 Largest Private Industrial Companies, Inc. 500
        - 0:2-4.15 Research and Development
          See also: MKT 60, PRODUCT DEVELOPMENT AND INTRODUCTION, selected subsections
          - 0:2-4.15.1 Expenditure Forecasts and Reviews, N.E.C.
            - 0:2-4.15.1.1 Battelle Memorial Institute Columbus Division series: Probable Levels of R&D Expenditures in (year): Forecast and Analysis
            - 0:2-4.15.1.2 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: Business' Plans for Research and Development Expenditures (annual)
            - 0:2-4.15.1.3 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: Annual Survey of Pollution Control Expenditures
            - 0:2-4.15.1.4 McGraw-Hill Department of Economics: Survey of Technological Breakthroughs and Widespread Application of Significant Technical Developments (discontinued)
              See also: MKT 50:2-1.44, Technological Forecasting; IOP 5:2-2.6, Technology Transfer, International
            - 0:2-4.15.1.5 National Science Foundation, National Patterns of R&D Resources; Funds and Manpower in the U.S. and Surveys of Science Resources
          - 0:2-4.15.2 Research and Development Philosophies, N.E.C.
            Commentary on such topics as: R&D's contribution to the economy; priorities of R&D efforts, etc.
          - 0:2-4.15.3 R&D Organization and Management, N.E.C.
            - 0:2-4.15.3.1 R&D Staff, N.E.C.
          - 0:2-4.15.4 Budgeting, Funding, Financial Control, and Resource Allocation of R&D
          - 0:2-4.15.5 Corporate/Marketing - R&D Interface
          - 0:2-4.15.6 Technology Assessment/Transfer
            See also: IOP 5:2-2.6, Technology Transfer, International
        - 0:2-4.16 Small Business (Box 7)
          - 0:2-4.16.1 Small Business; Its Role and Problems, N.E.C.
          - 0:2-4.16.2 Starting and Managing a Small Business
          - 0:2-4.16.3 Reports of the Select Committee on Small Business of the U.S. Senate
          - 0:2-4.16.4 The Small Business Administration: What it is; What it does
            - 0:2-4.16.4.1 SBA Publications, N.E.C.
              For example, Management Aids for Small Manufacturers; Small Marketer Aids; Technical Aids for Small Manufacturers; Small Business Bulletins; Management Research Summaries
      - 0:2-5 Executive Management; N.E.C. (functions in combination; general treatises on executive characteristics)
        See also: ADM 0:2-7, General Management, N.E.C.; selected subsections for ethnics and women as executives and in general management
        - 0:2-5.1 Executive Isolation
        - 0:2-5.2 Executive Motivation
          See also: MKT 50:2-1.2, Behavioral Analysis/Science; Attitude/Motivational Research, N.E.C.
        - [Executive Status Symbols--see: ADM 0:2-8.4.4, Compensation, Management, Perquisities (Perks)]
        - 0:2-5.3 U.S. Vis-a-vis Overseas Executives
        - [External Affairs Management--see: ADM 0:2-10, Public Affairs/Relations, all subsections]
      - 0:2-6 Financial Management
        See also: MKT 40:1-4, Financial/Credit Management
        - 0:2-6.1 Budgeting and Capital Management, N.E.C.
          Includes information on managing the budget function
          - 0:2-6.1.1 Capital Budgeting
            Includes information on capital investment analysis and control, the cost of capital, etc.
          - 0:2-6.1.2 Contingency Planning
          - 0:2-6.1.3 ROI (Return on Investment)
          - 0:2-6.1.4 Zero-Base Budgeting
        - 0:2-6.2 Business Finance, N.E.C.
          Includes information on financial planning; see also: IOP 5:3, Financial Aspects of Overseas Operations, selected subsections.
        - 0:2-6.3 Cost Control and Reduction in Business (as a profit improvement factor)
        - 0:2-6.4 Financial Manuals
        - 0:2-6.5 Financial Models and Modeling
        - 0:2-6.6 Profit Planning
          See also: ADM 0:2-4, Economics Management, miscellaneous subsections for information on the Profit System.
      - 0:2-7 General Management, N.E.C. (Box 8)
        The nature, philosophies, principles, science and concepts of administration; includes information on management power; see also: all ADM Subject Headings - and cross-references - for principles/techniques peculiar to specific functions, e.g. Economics Management, Financial Management, Personnel Relations, Public Relations, etc. Additionally, see all Sales Series (SAL) headings for the application of general management techniques in the selling process.
        - 0:2-7.1 Accountability (Results-Oriented Concept)
        - [CPM--see: ADM 0:2-7.4.2, Planning Methods, PERT, CPM, RAMPS, etc.]
        - [Cognitive Dissonance--see: ADM 0:2-7.6, Decision-Making]
        - 0:2-7.2 Communications (Manager/Manager and Manager/Subordinate, Personal) Techniques, N.E.C.
          See also: ADM 0:2-10, Public Affairs/Relations, all subsections, for information on organizational-corporate communications; SAL 5:6, Sales, Self-Development, all subsections)
          - 0:2-7.2.1 Brainstorming
          - 0:2-7.2.2 Business Calls
          - 0:2-7.2.3 Committees
          - 0:2-7.2.4 Computer Literacy
          - 0:2-7.2.5 Conferences, Conventions, Seminars and Meetings, N.E.C. (Box 9)
            See also: ADM 0:2-10.24, Meetings, Annual; ADM 0:2-10.25, Meetings, Employee; and SAL 25, SALES MEETINGS, and subsections
            - 0:2-7.2.5.1 Directories of Meeting Sites
            - 0:2-7.2.5.2 Problem-Solving Conferences
            - 0:2-7.2.5.3 Tele-Text/Terminal and Videoconferences
              See also: ADM 0:2-7.2.12, Visual and Instructional Aids
          - 0:2-7.2.6 Information Systems and Retrieval, (Files 26-25)
          - 0:2-7.2.6 Information Systems and Retrieval, (Files 24-1) (Box 10)
            See also: MKT 40:5, Marketing Intelligence and Information Systems, all subsections; MKT 50:7-1, Techniques of Information Gathering; SAL 10:5-2, Call Reports/Reporting, for information on sales force feedback
          - 0:2-7.2.7 Language Usage (Box 11)
            See also: SAL 5:6-8, Sales, Speaking, Listening and Vocabulary Building
          - 0:2-7.2.8 Listening
            - 0:2-7.2.8.1 Listening, Speaking, Writing (in combination)
          - [Meetings--see: ADM 0:2-7.2.5, Conferences, Seminars and Meetings, N.E.C. and subsections; see also: ADM 0:210.24, Meetings, Annual; ADM 0:2-10.25, Meetings, Employee; SAL 25, SALES MEETINGS, and subsections]
          - 0:2-7.2.9 Reading
            See also: ADV 40:3, Readership, all subsections
          - 0:2-7.2.10 Speaking
          - 0:2-7.2.11 Statistics, Use of
          - [Telephone--see: SAL 40:17, Telemarketing and references included there]
          - 0:2-7.2.12 Visual and Instructional Aids
            See also: ADM 0:2-7.2.5.3, Tele-Text/Terminal and Videoconferences; ADM 0:2-8.21.9, Learning Process/Memory/Forgetting; ADM 0:2-8.21.9.1, Programmed Instruction and Teaching Machines
          - 0:2-7.2.13 Writing
            See also: ADV 50:4-5, Copywriting; MKT 50:4, Research Report Writing; SAL 5:6-7, Sales, Reading and Writing
            - 0:2-7.2.13.1 Technical Writing
        - 0:2-7.3 Consultants (Box 12)
          See also: MKT 40:1-6, Marketing Consultants
        - 0:2-7.4 Control Techniques, N.E.C.
          - 0:2-7.4.1 Paperwork Control
          - 0:2-7.4.2 Planning Methods (PERT, CPM, RAMPS, etc.)
          - 0:2-7.4.3 Time Conservation
            See also: SAL 5:6-5, Sales, Management and Control of Time
        - 0:2-7.5 Creative Techniques and Creativity
          See also: ADV 5:10-3, Creative Staff, N.E.C.; MKT 60:1-1, Product Innovation, Development, Planning and Management, N.E.C.
        - 0:2-7.6 Decision-Making
          See also: MKT 40:4, Decision-Making in Marketing, all subsections; ADM 0:2-7.24, Systems Theory in Management
        - 0:2-7.7 Delegation
        - [Ethics: Social and Moral Responsibilities--see: ADM 0:2-10.32, Social and Ethical Responsibilities, Corporate, and all other references listed there]
        - 0:2-7.8 Ethnics/Minorities in Management
          See also: MKT 40:3-1.1, Ethnics/Minorities in Marketing; MKT 40:3-2.1, Ethnics/Minorities in Communications; SAL 5:3, Ethnics/Minorities in Selling
        - 0:2-7.9 Free-Form Concept (Box 13)
        - 0:2-7.10 Group Management Concept
        - 0:2-7.11 Human Values in Management: Human Relations; Manager/Manager Relations - Manager/Subordinate Relations
          See also: ADM 0:2-8, Personnel Management and Relations, all subsections
        - 0:2-7.12 Management by Objectives (MBO)
        - 0:2-7.13 Management Types, N.E.C.
          - 0:2-7.13.1 Innovators
          - 0:2-7.13.2 Organization Men/Women
          - 0:2-7.13.3 Production Wizards
          - 0:2-7.13.4 Specialists vs. Generalists
          - 0:2-7.13.5 Technical Management
        - 0:2-7.14 Matrix Management